Guide to the Sir Terence Clark photograph collection AD.MC.148
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Sir Terence Clark photograph collection
June 1965 - November 1968
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Clark, Terence
AD.MC.148
0.50 Linear Feet in 2 boxes comprised of 61 photographic prints in one album, 98 color photographic slides and an equal number of photographic prints of the same slides in a second box.
Photographic prints (61) mounted in one album, as well as color photographic slides (98), and copy prints, depicting scenes and events in the emirates of Dubai, Sharjah, Fujairah, and other locations in the Trucial States, dating from Sir Terence Clark's tenure as a diplomat (Assistant Political Agent) based in the Political Agency of Great Britain in Dubai, from 1965 to 1968.
Conditions governing access
The collection is open for use in the Reading Room of the Archives and Special Collections department of the NYU Abu Dhabi Library.
Immediate source of acquisition
Acquired by purchase, 2025.
Arrangement
The colllection is arranged largely by format. Prints that are housed in the album have remained in their original order, and are described in the finding aid at the page level. The photographic prints and slides contain the same images, simply in different formats, with the slides arranged in roughly chronological order and the prints arranged by location and topic.
Biographical note
Sir Terence J. Clark, KBE, CMG, CVO, served as a British diplomat in multiple postings between 1955 and his retirement in 1994. He was born on 12 June 1934, and after attending Thomas Parmiter's School in London, he joined the Royal Air Force, serving from 1953-1955. During that time, he studied Russian at the School of Slavonic Studies at Cambridge, and following his joining the Foreign Service, he studied Arabic at the School of Oriental and African Studies (SOAS), and then the Middle East Center for Arabic Studies (MECAS) in Lebanon from 1956-1957.
While he served in a variety of postings throughout his diplomatic career, most of the emphasis was on the Middle East and North Africa, which led him to postings in Bahrain,(1957-58); Amman [Jordan], (1958-60); Casablanca [Morocco], (1961-62); Dubai (1965-1968), where he served as Assistant Political Agent; Tripoli [Libya], (February-March 1981), where he served as Chargé d'Affaires; and Muscat [Oman], where he was Head of Chancery (1972-1973). His career culminated in appointments as Ambassador to Iraq (1985-1989) and Ambassador to Oman (1990-1994). Following his retirement from the Foreign Service, he remained active as the Chair of the British-Omani Society from 1995-2004, as director of the Middle East Association, and as a senior consultant at Middle East Consultants. He also served as director of the International Crisis Group's Sarajevo project in 1996.
Sources: webpage for the British Omani Society, accessed in March 2025: https://www.britishomani.org/team/sir-terence-clark
Wikipedia, accessed in March 2025: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terence_Clark.
Description of transcript of interview with Sir Terence Clark, 2002, British Diplomatic Oral History Programme, Churchill Archives Centre, University of Cambridge, accessed March 2025: https://archivesearch.lib.cam.ac.uk/repositories/9/archival_objects/431490
Content Description
Photographic prints (61) mounted in one album, as well as color photographic slides (98), and copy prints, depicting scenes and events in the emirates of Dubai, Sharjah, Fujairah, and Ras al Khaimah, dating from Clark's tenure as a diplomat (Assistant Political Agent) based in the Political Agency of Great Britain in Dubai, from 1965 to 1968.
The album contains many images of meetings with various political leaders and dignitaries, including the ruler of Dubai, Sheikh Rashid bin Said al Maktoum, rulers of neighboring emirates, such as Abu Dhabi, Ajman, Umm al-Qawain, Ras al-Khaimah, Sharjah, and Fujairah, as well as King Hussein of Jordan, and various British diplomats stationed in the Gulf region. A number of the images were taken during the visit of King Hussein of Jordan to Dubai in 1967, and several of the images of leaders of the various Emirates of the Trucial States may have also originated from this event. Other images depict meetings between the staff of the British Political Agency and the leader of Dubai, Sheikh Rashid bin Said al Maktoum, as well as the opening of the Dubai Zoo in 1967. Many of the photographs were taken by official photographers, with some containing the attribution on the verso of the images of the agency Photo Press International, and the photographer Noor Ali Rashid. Others are unattributed and may have been taken by Clark, such as the images on Dubai Creek, or by staff of the Political Agency.
The color slides, while including a few images of Dubai, chiefly document visits to the east coast of the Trucial States, in particular the towns of Khor Fakkan and Dibba, and other locations in the emirate of Fujairah. Many images depict fisherman bringing in their catch, as well as various types of boats used in and around the town of Khor Fakkan. Other images focus on villagers and farmers, either on the east coast, or the inland areas of Sharjah emirate. A couple of images also depict Al Jahili fort in Al Ain (Buraimi), at that time used as a base for the Trucial Oman Scouts.
Diplomats -- Great Britain; United Arab Emirates -- Kings and rulers.; Dubayy (United Arab Emirates: Emirate); Fujayrah (United Arab Emirates: Emirate); Khawr Fakkān (United Arab Emirates); Hussein, King of Jordan, 1935-1999
- Photo album
  - Terence Clark, holding monkey, walking with Sheikh Ahmad bin Ali Al Thani, ruler of Qatar, at opening of Dubai Zoo, undated, circa 1967 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page [inside front cover])
  - Visit of King Hussein of Jordan (3 images) (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 1)
    General
    Images: 1. King Hussein posing with rulers of the Emirates of Ras al Khaimah, Umm al Qawain, Fujairah, Ajman, and Sharjah. 2. Sheikh Ahmad bin Rashid al Mualla (ruler of Umm al Qawain) and Sheikh Khalid bin Muhammad al Qasimi (ruler of Sharjah). 3. Sheikh Saqr bin Muhammad al Qasimi (ruler of Ras al Khaimah), Sheikh Zayed bin Sultan al Nahyan (ruler of Abu Dhabi) and Terence Clark.
  - Various (3 images), undated, circa 1967 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 2)
    Images (top to bottom of page): 1. Seated, left to right, Sheikh Rashid bin Said al Maktoum (ruler of Dubai), David Roberts (Political Agent, Dubai), Sheikh Muhammad bin Hamad al Sharqi (ruler of Fujairah), Terence Clark (Asst. Political Agent). 2. Walking down stairs, left to right, Terence Clark, David Roberts, Sheikh Rashid bin Said al Maktoum. 3. Seated around table, left to right, Major Tim Budd (Trucial Oman Scouts), Sheikh Rashid bin Said al Maktoum, Terence Clark, Colonel Pat Ive (COMTOS), and standing, on right, is Aminallah Farooghi, Headmaster, Iranian School, Dubai.
  - Arrival for the opening of the Dubai Zoo, undated, circa 1967 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 3)
    Contents of page
    Images, top to bottom of page: 1. left to right, Sheikh Rashid bin Said al Maktoum (ruler of Dubai), entering zoo with Sheikh Ahmad bin 'Ali al Thani (ruler of Qatar) and Otto Bulart (director of zoo). 2. Group at entrance of zoo. 3. left to right, Sheikh Rashid bin Said al Maktoum (partially obscured), Terence Clark, Sheikh Ahmad bin 'Ali al Thani.
  - Unidentified event [possibly during visit of King Hussein], ruler of Dubai and others (3 images), undated, circa 1967 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 4)
    Images from top to bottom of page: 1. left to right, Sheikh Saqr bin Muhammad al Qasimi (ruler of Ras al Khaimah), Sheikh Khalid bin Saqr al Qasimi, Trevor Bevan (commandant, Ras al Khaimah Police). 2. Sheikh Khalid bin Saqr al Qasimi, Major David Neild (Trucial Oman Scouts), Yvonne Keirl (British Bank of the Middle East), Trevor Bevan, Tim Ashe (D.I.O., Ras al Khaimah). 3. in foreground, Sheikh Saqr bin Muhammad al Qasimi, in background, Robert Mackay (Digdaga Research Farm), Trevor Bevan, Tim Ashe, Chris Keirl (British Bank of the Middle East), Margaret Mackay.
  - Unidentified event [possibly visit of King Hussein], ruler of Dubai and others (2 images), undated, circa 1967 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 5)
    Images from top to bottom: 1. Sheikh Rashid bin Said al Maktoum (Dubai) with Sheikh Khalid bin Muhammad al Qasimi (Sharjah). 2. Terence Clark seated next to Sheikh Rashid bin Said al Maktoum, with Amin Farooghi (Iranian School, Dubai) standing behind them.
  - Unidentified event [possibly visit of King Hussein], rulers of various Emirates and British diplomats (3 images), undated, circa 1967 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 6)
    Images from top to bottom: 1. Sheikh Rashid bin Said al Maktoum (Dubai) speaking with David Roberts (Political Agent) and Terence Clark (Assistant Political Agent). 2. Rulers of Dubai, Ras al Khaimah, Sharjah and Abu Dhabi, conferring together. 3. Standing at table, left to right: Terence Clark, Sheikh Humaid bin Rashid al Nu'aimi (Ajman), Sheikh Khalid bin Muhammad al Qasimi (Sharjah), Sheikh Hamad bin Muhammad al Sharqi (Fujairah), Sheikh Zayed bin Sultan al Nahyan (Abu Dhabi), Sheikh Saqr bin Muhammad al Qasimi (Ras al Khaimah).
  - Unidentified events (2 images), undated, circa 1967 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 7)
    Images from top to bottom: 1. Terence Clark, seated at table with Rashid Mabrooshi (Dubai Airport Immigration) and Sheikh Humaid bin Rashid al Nu'aimi (Ajman). 2. Terence Clark, seated with Muhammad Said, director of Kuwait State Office, Squadron Leader John Parker (commander of Royal Air Force Base in Sharjah), and others.
  - Visit of King Hussein of Jordan to Dubai (2 images), [1967] (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 8)
    Images from top to bottom: Sheikh Rashid bin Said al Maktoum (ruler of Dubai) seated and speaking with King Hussein. 2. Standing, left to right, Terence Clark, David Roberts, Bill Duff (financial advisor to Sheikh Rashid bin Said), King Hussein.
  - Visit of King Hussein of Jordan to Dubai (2 images), [1967] (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 9)
    Images from top to bottom: 1. Standing, left to right, Terence Clark, David Roberts, Bill Duff, King Hussein. 2. Terence Clark (Assistant Political Agent, Dubai) speaking with King Hussein of Jordan.
  - Scenes from Dubai Creek (3 images), undated, circa 1967 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 10)
    Images from top to bottom: 1. Friday Mosque, behind wind towers. 2. Captain's stores. 3. Dubai Customs, Sheikh Rashid's counting house.
  - Scenes from Dubai Creek (3 images), undated, circa 1967 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 11)
    Images from top to bottom: Ruler of Dubai's father's former house [Shindagha district]. 2. Bridge across Creek. 3. Souq wharf.
  - Scenes from Dubai Creek (3 images), undated, circa 1967 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 12)
    Images from top of page to bottom: 1. British Political Agency, Dubai. 2. Assistant Political Agent's house. 3. Abra (ferry) across Dubai Creek.
  - Scenes from Dubai Creek (3 images), undated, circa 1967 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 13)
    Images from top to bottom of page: 1. Boom [type of boat] at Darwish Steps. 2. Looking towards Carlton Hotel. 3. Dubai Customs.
  - Ruler of Dubai training falcons at Za'abil Palace (3 images), November 1966 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 14)
    Images from top to bottom: unlabeled in album, but depict 1. Sheikh Rashid bin Said seated on bench, holding falcon. 2. Falcon handler standing, holding falcon, next to another man, with Land Rover in background. 3. Falcon handler holding falcon, while crouching on ground.
  - Various images, Dubai (3), undated, circa 1966-1967 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 15)
    Images from top to bottom of page: 1. Unlabeled, depicting falcon handler with falcon on the ground. 2. Ruler of Dubai's yacht, "Za'abil." 3. Smugglers cook lunch on Zarawani's launch.
  - East coast (3 images), undated, circa 1966 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 16)
    Images from top to bottom of page: 1. Hamad bin Hamid, Wali of Husn Dibba, Sharjah. 2. Sharqi tribesman, Dibba Bay. 3. Abdullah bin Alai, Wali of Dibba, Fujairah, and son Muhammad.
  - East coast (4 images), undated, circa 1966 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 17)
    Images from top to bottom: 1. Dibba tribesman, Muhammad bin Abdallah, wali's son. 2. Muhammad bin Said of Muraba. 3. Sheikh Saif bin Muhammad, Wali of Fujairah. 4. Women drawing water, Fujairah.
  - East coast (3 images), undated, circa 1966 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 18)
    Images from top to bottom of page: 1. and 2. 'Ali, o/c Police, Khor Fakkan. 3. Wadi, near Masafi.
  - Buraimi (4 images), undated, circa 1966 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 19)
    Images from top to bottom of page: 1. and 2. Trucial Oman Scouts headquarters, Buraimi Fort [Al Jahili Fort, Al 'Ain]. 3. and 4. Camel souq, Buraimi [Al 'Ain].
  - Terence Clark with various local personalities (3 images), including Sheikh Rashid bin Humaid al Nu'aimi (rule of Ajman), undated, circa 1966-1967 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page 20)
    Images from top to bottom of page: 1. Standing, left to right, Head of Iranian Red Lion and Sun (unnamed), Amin Farooghi, Terence Clark, Sheikh Rashid bin Humain al Nu'aimi, unidentified, Sheikh Humaid bin Rashin al Nu'aimi. 2. Terence Clark with Kemal Hamza, Director, Dubai Municipality. 3. Terence Clark with 'Ali, the head of the Saudi Office, Dubai, and Ibrahim, from the Kuwait State Office, Dubai, and one unidentified person.
  - Terence Clark greeting Sir William (Bill) Luce, Political Resident, Persian Gulf, at airfield (2 images), undated, circa 1966-1967 (Box 1, Volume 1, Page [inside back cover])
- Photographic slides, 1965-1968
  - November - December 1965 (20 slides) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - January - March 1966 (20 slides) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - March 1966 (20 slides) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - March 1966 - February 1967 (20 slides) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - February 1967 - December 1968 (18 slides) (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Prints (copies of slides), 1965-1968
  - Bedouin villagers (13 prints), December 1966 - April 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dubai Creek (11 prints), November 1965 - December 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - East coast: Dibba, Fujairah, and unidentified locales (15 prints), March 1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - East coast: Khor Fakkan (fishermen, boats, scenery, 26 images), March 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Falconers and falcons (9 images), December 1965, January 1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Farmers and villagers, unidentified locales (4 images), March 1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Inland locales: Sharjah (Dhaid, Mleiha, Wadi Tayyib) and Abu Dhabi (Buraimi)(6 images), March 1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Various, including Sheikh Rashid bin Humaid al-Nu'aimi (ruler of Ajman), and seacraft (5), December 1966 - April 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Village scenes: Sharjah and unidentified locales, December 1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)